Juliet Brooke Ballard Papers
Juliet Brooke Ballard Papers
1935-1992
Ballard, Juliet Brooke.
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, poet. Author of books based on the Edgar Cayce readings. Correspondence, typescript poems, research material on Edgar Cayce, photographs, published material, including articles and clippings by and about Ballard, scrapbooks, and memorabilia.
148829
Biographical History
Juliet Ballard (1913-) attended Mary Baldwin Seminary, Stuart Hall, Randolph-Macon Women's College, and the Richmond School of Social Work. For a time she was a social worker, but soon made poetry her main interest. A member of the American Poetry League, her published poems include Under a Tropic Sun and Winter has Come, and she was a frequent contributor to magazines including Wings, Nature, Canadian Poetry Magazine, and many others.
She was also interested in psychic and occult phenomena and was the author of several books based on Edgar Cayce's work, including The Hidden Laws of Earth and Treasures from Earth's Storehouse..
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Juliet Brooke Ballard Papers include correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters, as well as some correspondence filed by subject; the latter consists of fragments which Ballard cut from incoming correspondence which give opinions of her work.
Subject files contains a notice of an award, a calendar, membership cards for the American Poetry League, a photograph of Ballard, and a program.
Manuscripts contains an undated typescript copy of The Shadow and the Sun and Other Poems, and a typescript of a 1956 interview.
Published material contains articles and poems about and by Ballard and others, books by Ballard, and newspaper clippings by and about her and others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically (incoming) or chronologically (outgoing). Subject files and published material are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Religion and philosophy; Women Authors; Ballard, Juliet Brooke Archives.; Cayce, Edgar, 1877-1945.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Conduct of life.; Occultism.; Women authors, American.; Women poets, American.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence, A-Z and unidentified, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1959 (Box 1)
  - By subject, opinions of Ballard's work, clippings (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Award (Box 1)
  - Calendar (Box 1)
  - Membership cards, American Poetry League, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Photograph (Box 1)
  - Program - meeting of the General Society of the War of 1812, 1956 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Poems
    - The Shadow and the Sun and Other Poems, typescript (Box 1)
  - Radio interview, typescript (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Articles and poems
    - About Ballard, 1956 (Box 2)
    - By Ballard, 1935; 1945,; 1956,; 1959-1959 (Box 2)
    - About others (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Under a Tropic Sun, 2 copies (Box 2)
    - Winter Has Come (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About Ballard (Box 2)
    - By Ballard (Box 2)
    - About others (Box 2)